Pranshu Nijhawan

Engineering Leader | SaaS Architect

+91-9999966272

https://www.linkedin.com/in/pranshunijhawan/

mail@pranshunijhawan.dev

https://www.pranshunijhawan.dev/



SUMMARY

Engineering leader with **9+ years** in solution architecture, product development, cloud strategy, and DevOps. **Engineering Manager & Architect** at McKinsey, driving large-scale SaaS with 99.9% uptime. Built SearchSphere & Orchestron, optimizing AI search, ETL, and data processing, saving millions. Expert in microservices, Kubernetes, serverless, and analytics.

EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer 2

m March 2022 - Present

McKinsey & Company

- Architectural Leadership & Design: Architected SearchSphere and Orchestron using Al-driven orchestration, vectorization, RAG, .NET, Spark, and Kubernetes for scalable, modular solutions. Led architectural assessments, ADRs, and tech OKRs for strategic alignment.
- Team Leadership & Development: Leading a team of 28 engineers, including 5 tech leads, overseeing skill development, career growth, and performance management.
- Scalable ETL System Engineering: Engineered a zero-downtime ETL platform processing 200M+ records in under 15 minutes using Databricks, Spark, ADF, and PostgreSQL, leveraging Blue/Green slotting and CDC for scalability and reliability.
- Cross-Functional Collaboration & Compliance: Led SOC2 certification initiative, collaborating with Infosec and compliance teams to ensure regulatory alignment.
- Future Architecture Roadmap Management: Orchestrated the management of the Future Architecture Runway, optimizing the product roadmap, increasing delivery efficiency by 25%.

Principal Engineer

April 2021 – March 2022

Condeco, now Eptura

- Architectural Leadership & Design: Architected an Intelligent Distributed Release Management Platform with Serverless Functions, Azure IoT Hub, and CosmosDB, orchestrating updates for 300M+ devices.
- Team Leadership & Development: Leading a team of 20 engineers, including 4 tech leads and 18 developers across 4 squads.
- Scalable Distributed Platform Engineering: Engineered scalable distributed systems using React, C#, .NET, and serverless architectures.

Senior Engineer

m December 2019 - April 2021

Nagarro

- Developed web and cloud applications for Nagarro clients across E-Commerce, Employee Management, and Inventory Systems using Angular, Ionic, and .NET Core.
- Established CI/CD pipelines and implemented database architecture using Code-First/DB-First with EF Core and SQL scripts for schemas and stored procedures.

Software Engineer

■ September 2018 - December 2019

Condeco, now Eptura

- Lead the design, development, and enhancement of Condeco's Workspace Management Platform, using C#, .NET, React, SQL Server etc.
- Developed scalable microservices, managed CI/CD infrastructure, documented with Data-Flow Diagrams, and contributed to data architecture.

Associate Software Engineer

m February 2016 - August 2018

Gartner

• Led the design and development of ClearForce, Gartner's Survey Platform, an employee engagement SaaS, using C#, .NET Core, and React, managing UI enhancements and bug fixes.

SKILLS

- Languages C#, JavaScript, TypeScript, Python, Java, SQL
- Frameworks and Tools .NET, Node.JS, React, Angular, GraphQL, PostgreSQL, SQL Server, Azure, AWS, Databricks
- Concepts Cloud Architecture, OOPS, Microservices, Domain Driven Architecture, Data Streaming

KEY ACHIEVEMENTS

SearchSphere

Designed and architected a fully configurable Multi-Tenant Search Platform using Typescript, Node.JS, and PostgreSQL, leveraging vectorization and Retrieval Augmented Generation (RAG) techniques to enable both global and dimension-based searching with the ability to onboard new dimensions without any code changes, resulting in a successful decommissioning Elasticsearch, which resulted in cost savings of over \$2 million.

Zero-Downtime ETL platform

Engineered a highly scalable and reliable platform using Databricks, Spark, Azure Data Factory, and PostgreSQL based on Blue/Green slotting strategy processing over 200 million records across 100+ tables in under 15 minutes using CDC techniques and dynamic schema allocation strategies.

Orchestron

Architected a high-performance Data Processing and Explosion platform utilizing .NET and Spark on a Kubernetes infrastructure featuring a modular architecture with configurable rules and a plug-and-play design for seamless data transformation and explosion managed by Generative AI Agents for intelligent orchestration and rule management.

Intelligent Distributed Release Management Platform

Developed a Platform, leveraging Serverless Functions, Azure IoT Hub, and Azure CosmosDB Orchestrating platform updates across 300+ million devices using scalable techniques such as fan-out/fan-in workflows, backed by robust monitoring frameworks and emergency rollback mechanisms.

CERTIFICATIONS

- Microsoft Certified: Azure Data Engineer Associate
- Microsoft Certified: Azure Developer Associate
- AWS Certified Developer Associate

EDUCATION

Gurgaon Institute of Technology & Management

2012 - 2016, B.Tech, Computer Science & Engineering